Confederate States of America Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Confederate States of America Records 1854-1889 1861-1865
MSS16550
Confederate States of America
18,500 items
124 containers plus 5 oversize
28 linear feet
71 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, proclamations, messages of the president, court cases, minute books, docket books, customs records, financial records, letterbooks, orders, reports, and other records of the Confederate Department of Justice, Department of State, Department of the Treasury, Post Office Department, Navy Department, and War Department. Includes Confederate constitutional documents and the James Wolcott Wadsworth collection of diplomatic correspondence and letters of Raphael Semmes.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Bolling--Correspondence.; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893--Correspondence.; Benjamin, J. P. (Judah Philip), 1811-1884--Correspondence.; Clay, C. C. (Clement Claiborne), 1816-1882--Correspondence.; Conger, Lewis--Correspondence.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889--Correspondence.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889.; DeLeon, Edwin, 1828-1891--Correspondence.; Guirot, Anthony J.--Correspondence.; Helm, Charles J.--Correspondence.; Heyliger, Lewis--Correspondence.; Hotze, Henry, 1833-1887--Correspondence.; Lamar, L. Q. C. (Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus), 1825-1893--Correspondence.; Mann, A. Dudley (Ambrose Dudley), 1801-1889--Correspondence.; Mason, J. M. (James Murray), 1798-1871--Correspondence.; Memminger, C. G. (Christopher Gustavus), 1803-1888--Correspondence.; Pickett, John T. (John Thomas), 1822-1884--Correspondence.; Quintero, John A.--Correspondence.; Reagan, John H. (John Henninger), 1818-1905--Correspondence.; Semmes, Raphael, 1809-1877--Correspondence.; Slidell, John, 1793-1871--Correspondence.; Stephens, Alexander H. (Alexander Hamilton), 1812-1883--Correspondence.; Thompson, Jacob, 1810-1885--Correspondence.; Trescott, William Henry, 1822- --Correspondence.; Wadsworth, James Wolcott, 1846-1926. James Wolcott Wadsworth collection.; Walker, Leroy Pope, 1817-1884--Correspondence.; Yancey, William Lowndes, 1814-1863--Correspondence.
Organizations
Confederate States of America.; Confederate States of America.; Confederate States of America. Army of Tennessee--Surgeons.; Confederate States of America. Army of Tennessee. Register of surgeons. 1861-1865.; Confederate States of America. Congress.; Confederate States of America. Constitution.; Confederate States of America. Department of Justice. Confederate States of America. Department of Justice records.; Confederate States of America. Department of State. Confederate States of America. Department of State records.; Confederate States of America. Department of the Treasury. Confederate States of America. Department of the Treasury records.; Confederate States of America. Navy. Confederate States of America. Navy records.; Confederate States of America. Post-Office Department. Confederate States of America. Post-Office Department records.; Confederate States of America. War Department. Confederate States of America. War Department records.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, Confederate.; Executive departments--Confederate States of America.; Legislative bodies--Confederate States of America.
Places
Belgium--Foreign relations--Confederate States of America.; Confederate States of America--Armed forces.; Confederate States of America--Foreign relations--Belgium.; Confederate States of America--Foreign relations--France.; Confederate States of America--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Confederate States of America--Foreign relations--Mexico.; Confederate States of America--Officials and employees.; Confederate States of America--Politics and government.; France--Foreign relations--Confederate States of America.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Confederate States of America.; Mexico--Foreign relations--Confederate States of America.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Titles
Confederate States of America Records at the Library of Congress
Acquisition Information
The records of the Confederate States of America, also known as the Pickett Papers, were purchased by the United States in 1872 from John T. Pickett, former diplomatic agent of the Confederacy, and transferred by the Department of the Treasury to the Library of Congress in 1906 and 1910. Other items received by gift, purchase, or transfer also comprise part of the collection, including approximately one hundred additions between 1898 and 1956. The James Wolcott Wadsworth Collection was given to the Library as an addition to the records by James W. Wadsworth in 1926. The Department of the Treasury also transferred a large group of Confederate treasury records in 1920, and in 1921, much of the material processed as part of the War Department series was received from descendants of Confederate officers.
Additional Guides
State Department records are described in The Handbook of Manuscripts in the Library of Congress (1918), pp. 70-75, and published in part in the Official Records of Union and Confederate Navies in the War of the Rebellion, Series II, Volume 3. The Librarians Annual Reports note the arrival of other material.
Transfers
Some photographs, lithographs, and illustrative material have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the Confederate States of America are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on seventy-one reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Online Content
The records of the Confederate States of America are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000027. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition as available.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Confederate States of America span the years 1854-1889, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1861-1865. The collection relates to the formation of the government of the Confederacy and the conduct of its internal, external, and military affairs.
With few exceptions, the collection consists of official or semiofficial records generated by departments of the Confederate government and their agents. The departments of state, justice, treasury, navy, and war and the post office are represented, along with material relating to the president, the congress, and the constitution.
Most numerous are the records of the Department of State containing correspondence exchanged for most of the period between Secretary of State Judah P. Benjamin and departmental agents and diplomats abroad, particularly those stationed in Belgium, France, Great Britain, and Mexico. The records are supplemented by the inclusion of the James Wolcott Wadsworth Collection of similar material. Other records of the department relate to administrative and financial affairs, passports, pardons, appointments to office, applications for office, and maritime and domestic affairs of the Confederacy. As noted below, the records of the Department of State were once known as the "Pickett Papers."
The records of the treasury and post office departments are chiefly concerned with subordinate offices. The records of the War Department contain early correspondence of the secretary of war, general orders, strength returns, muster rolls and quartermaster records. Justice Department material consists of records of Confederate courts in Alabama, Louisiana, and Mississippi.
Proclamations, messages, and other papers of President Jefferson Davis, acts and resolutions of the Confederate congress, material relating to the constitution and secession, and miscellaneous items complete the collection. A Miscellany series includes documents relating to the state governments of Georgia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia, printed and published material covering the statues and proclamations of the Confederate government, and blank official forms.
Prior to the evacuation of Richmond, Virginia, by the Confederate government, Judah P. Benjamin ordered the records packed in wooden cases for removal from the capital and placed them in the custody of the chief clerk of the department, William J. Bromwell. Bromwell hid the records of in a barn near Charlotte, North Carolina. Following a quarrel with Benjamin, Bromwell disclosed the location of the records to John T. Pickett, who had been a Confederate agent in Mexico and whose personal papers are also in the Library of Congress. Pickett sold the records to the United States in 1872 for $75,000. Among the nearly one hundred additions was the transfer in 1920 of a group of Confederate treasury records from the United States Treasury Department. In 1921, much material now in the War Department series was received from descendants of Confederate officers. The series entitled Additions consists of several miscellaneous groups of records formerly organized under separate headings. The material consists chiefly of Confederate financial bonds.
Correspondence of many of the leading officials of the Confederate States appears in the records. In addition to the dominant figure, Secretary of State Judah P. Benjamin, other correspondents include Bolling Baker, G. T. Beauregard, Clement C. Clay, Lewis Conger, Jefferson Davis, Edwin DeLeon, Anthony J. Guirot, Charles J. Helm, Lewis Heyliger, Henry Hotze, L. Q. C. Lamar, A. Dudley Mann, James M. Mason, Christopher G. Memminger, John T. Pickett, John A. Quintero, John H. Reagan, Raphael Semmes, John Slidell, Alexander Hamilton Stephens, Jacob Thompson, William H. Trescott, LeRoy P. Walker, and William Lowndes Yancey.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eleven series:
Department of State, 1859-1868
Executive and Legislative Branches of the Confederacy, 1861-1865
Confederate Constitutional Documents, 1861-1883
Department of Justice, 1860-1867
Department of the Treasury, 1860-1865
Post Office Department, 1861-1865
War Department, 1861-1865
Navy Department, 1861-1865
Miscellany, 1858-1872
Additions, 1854-1889
Oversize, 1854-1864
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 13,744
- Department of State, 1859-1868 (Box 1-65, Reel 1-35)
  - Diplomatic Missions, 1861-1868 (Box 1-7, Reel 1-6)
    Correspondence, instructions, dispatches, and related material exchanged between the Department of State and its representatives to other nations.
    Arranged by locality and chronologically therein. Listings of the principal commissioners are given where applicable.
    Access to digital content is provided for each reel. Note that in some cases, multiple series or subseries may appear on a single reel.
    - Washington, 1861 (Box 1, Reel 1 *)
      - Forsyth, John
      - Pickett, John T.
    - Virginia, Alexander Hamilton Stephens, 1861
    - Great Britain
      - 1861-1863
        - Fearn, Walker
        - Huger, Benjamin
        - MacFarland, J. E.
        - Mann, A. Dudley
        - Mason, James M.
        - Rost, Pierre A.
        - Slidell, John
        - Trescott, William H.
        - Yancey, William Lowndes
      - 1861-1864 (Box 2, Reel 2 *)
        - Mason, James M.
        - Spence, James
    - France, 1861-1864 (Box 3, Reel 3 *)
      - Thouvenel, M.
      - Slidell, John
    - Belgium, 1861-1864 (Box 4, Reel 4 *)
      - Davis, Jefferson
      - Mann, A. Dudley
      - Pius IX, Pope
    - Spain, Pierre A. Rost, 1861-1864
    - Papal States, P. N. Lynch, 1864
    - Mexico
      - 1861-1862, John T. Pickett
      - 1861-1868, John T. Pickett (Box 5, Reel 5 *)
      - 1861-1862, John T. Pickett (Box 6, Reel 5 *)
      - 1862-1865 (Box 7, Reel 6 *)
        - Cripps, John S.
        - Preston, William
        - Ricken, Charles
    - Russia, Lucius Q. C. Lamar, 1863
  - Consular and Other Missions, 1861-1865 (Box 7-17, Reel 6-10)
    Correspondence, instructions, dispatches, and related material exchanged between the Department of State and Confederate officials and agents in foreign countries.
    Arranged by locality and chronologically therein. Listings of the principal officials and agents are given where applicable.
    - Locality (Box 7, Reel 6 *)
      - Canada, 1864
        - Clay, Clement C.
        - Dawson, George
        - Holcombe, James P.
        - Lee, E. G.
        - Thompson, Jacob
      - Cork, Ireland, Robert Dowling, 1863-1864
      - Fort Brown, Tex., 1862
      - Havana, Cuba, 1861-1864
        - Helm, Charles J.
        - Magruder, J. B.
        - Pickett, John T.
      - Ireland, 1863-1864, undated
        - Bannon, John
        - Capstan, James L.
        - Hotze, Henry
        - Lalor, James F.
      - Italy, A. Dudley Mann, 1861-1862
      - London, England, Henry Hotze, 1861-1863 (Box 7, Reel 6 *)
      - London, England, Henry Hotze, 1862-1864 (Box 7, Reel 7 *)
      - Matamoras, Mexico, 1862-1864 (Box 8, Reel 8 *)
        - Avengo, Bernard
        - Fitzpatrick, Richard
        - Heyliger, Lewis
        - Slidell, John
      - Nassau and New Providence, Lewis Heyleiger, 1862-1864
      - New Leon and Coahuila, Mexico, John A. Quintero, 1861-1864, undated
      - Paris, France, 1862-1864 (Box 9, Reel 9 *)
        - DeLeon, Edwin
        - McRae, Colin
      - St. George's, Bermuda, Norman J. Walker, 1863-1864
      - Vera Cruz, Mexico, Emile LaSere, 1864
      - Miscellaneous translations, John Slidell, undated
    - Keys to the Confederate ciphers, undated
    - Special personal instructions to all agents, undated
    - Special commissions issued to agents, 1861-1865 (Box 10, Reel 10 *)
    - Instructions and dispatches, 1862-1865 (Box 11, Reel 10 *)
      - Agents
        - Avengo, Bernard
        - DeLeon, Edwin
        - Dowling, Robert
        - Fitzpatrick, Richard
        - Helm, Charles J.
        - Hotze, Henry
        - LaSere, Emile
        - Quintero, John A.
        - Walker, Norman J.
      - Cuba, 1861-1862 (Box 12, Reel 10 *)
      - Great Britain, 1861-1862
      - France, 1861-1862
      - Mexico, 1861-1862
      - Russia, Lucius Q. C. Lamar, 1862-1864 (Box 13, Reel 10 *)
      - Great Britain, 1862-1864 (Box 14, Reel 10 *)
        - Holcombe, James P.
        - Mason, James M.
      - France, 1862-1864 (Box 15, Reel 10 *)
        - Slidell, John
      - Belgium, A. Dudley Mann, 1862-1864 (Box 16, Reel 10 *)
      - Mexico, John A. Quintero, 1862-1864 (Box 17, Reel 10 *)
      - Papal States, P. N. Lynch, 1862-1864
      - Spain, Pierre A. Rost, 1862-1864
  - Foreign Consulates, 1861-1864 (Box 18, Reel 11 *)
    Correspondence and other related material with diplomatic representatives of foreign nations.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of country and chronologically therein.
    - Austria, 1862-1864 (Box 18, Reel 11 *)
    - Belgium, 1862-1864
    - Bremen, 1862
    - France, 1861-1864
      - La Question Americaine
      - Translations, Alfred Paul
    - Great Britain, 1861-1864, undated
    - Italy, 1861-1864
    - Netherlands, 1863
    - Prussia, 1864
    - Spain, 1861-1864
    - Miscellany
      - Raven, Ernst
      - Torrier, J.
  - Records, 1861-1865 (Box 19-25, Reel 12-15)
    Correspondence, memoranda, letters of marque, claims for damage, and other related material concerning marine, administrative, and domestic activities.
    Arranged by subject and chronologically therein.
    - Maritime, 1861-1863 (Box 19, Reel 12 *)
    - Administrative, 1861-1865 (Box 20, Reel 13 *)
    - Domestic, 1861-1865
      - Index to letters received, 1864 (Box 21, Reel 13 *)
      - Letters sent (Box 22, Reel 13 *)
        - 1861-1864
        - 1864-1865 (Box 23, Reel 13 *)
      - Letters received (Box 24, Reel 14 *)
        - 1861-1863
        - 1863-1865 (Box 25, Reel 15 *)
  - Property Files, 1862-1864 (Box 25-27, Reel 15-16)
    Correspondence, estimates, memoranda, and indexes relating to the loss and destruction of property in the Confederacy.
    Arranged by subject.
    - Slaves, 1862-1864 (Box 25, Reel 15 *)
    - Railroads, undated
    - Index to lists of property stolen or destroyed (Box 26, Reel 16 *)
      - Undated
      - Undated (Box 27, Reel 16 *)
  - Diary of Judah P. Benjamin, 1861-1864 (Box 28, Reel 16 *)
    A daily account of events from 22 Feb. 1862-12 Dec. 1864.
  - Financial Records, 1861-1865 (Box 29-34, Reel 17-19)
    Correspondence, accounts, receipts, records, memoranda, appropriations, estimates, checks, warrants, and ledgers relating to the expenses of the State Department and its agents.
    - Miscellany, 1861-1865 (Box 29, Reel 17 *)
    - Miscellany, 1861-1865 (Box 29, Reel 18 *)
    - Disbursing clerk's cash books, 1864-1865 (Box 30, Reel 19 *)
    - Diplomatic account book, 1861-1865 (Box 31, Reel 19 *)
    - Foreign service ledger, 1861-1865 (Box 32, Reel 19 *)
    - Appropriation expense record book, 1861-1865 (Box 33, Reel 19 *)
    - Departmental requests to the Treasury, 1861-1865 (Box 34, Reel 19 *)
  - Pardons and Passports, 1861-1865 (Box 35-38, Reel 20-21)
    Records of passports and pardons issued, applications for passports, lists, passports granted, and a record book.
    - Passport applications, 1861-1865 (Box 35, Reel 20 *)
    - Passport lists, undated
    - Blank passports
    - Passports issued with a descriptive list (Box 36, Reel 21 *)
      - 1863-1864
      - 1864-1865 (Box 37, Reel 21 *)
    - Pardon record book, 1862-1864 (Box 38, Reel 21 *)
  - Presidential Proclamation File, 1861-1865 (Box 39-40, Reel 21 *)
    Drafts, manuscript copies, and printed copies of proclamations and messages of Jefferson Davis and other leaders of the Confederacy.
    - Presidential proclamations, 1861-1865 (Box 39, Reel 21 *)
    - Manuscripts of proclamations, 1861-1864 (Box 40, Reel 21 *)
    - Printed messages of Jefferson Davis, 1862-1865
    - Printed proclamations, 1861
    - Proclamation of Queen Victoria, 1861
  - Public Office File, 1861-1865 (Box 41-47, Reel 22-25)
    Applications for office, records of commissions and appointments issued, confirmations of appointments, acting appointments, oaths of office, letters of resignation, and related correspondence.
    - Commissions and appointments (Box 41, Reel 22 *)
      - 1861-1862
      - 1862-1864 (Box 42, Reel 22 *)
    - Index to commissions and appointments, undated (Box 43, Reel 22 *)
    - Commissions and appointments, 1864-1865 (Box 44, Reel 22 *)
    - Record book of acting appointments, 1862-1864 (Box 45, Reel 22 *)
    - List of applications for appointments, undated (Box 46, Reel 23 *)
    - Applications for appointments, 1861-1862 (Box 46, Reel 23 *)
    - Applications for appointments, 1862-1865 (Box 46, Reel 24 *)
    - Senate confirmation of appointments, 1861-1865 (Box 46, Reel 24 *)
    - Correspondence relating to appointments, 1861-1865 (Box 47, Reel 25 *)
    - Oaths of office, 1861-1865
    - Letters of resignation, 1861-1864
  - Miscellany, 1859-1864 (Box 48-49, Reel 26 *)
    An address book, orders, resolutions, copyrights, prisoner exchange records, memoranda, printed forms, and miscellaneous material relating to Fort Sumter, S.C., foreign loans, Indian affairs, and Lord John Russell.
    - General (Box 48, Reel 26 *)
      - Address of the London Peace Society, London, England, to the people of the United States
      - Correspondence, 1859-1864
      - Books ordered by the State Department
      - Congressonal resolutions
      - Copyright records
      - Evacuation of Fort Sumter, S.C.
        - Anderson, Robert
        - Beauregard, G. T.
        - Campbell, John A.
        - Lincoln, Abraham
      - Exchange of prisoners
      - Foreign loans
        - Erlanger & Co.
        - Slidell, John
      - Indian affairs
      - Miscellaneous correspondents
      - Russell, John Russell, Earl (copies)
      - Secretary of state
    - Memoranda, 1863-1864
      - Cast-iron guns
      - Economic matters in Europe
      - Cost of armaments in France
    - Notes relating to printed forms
    - Printed forms, 1861-1865 (Box 49)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1860-1864 (Box 50-52, Reel 27-28)
    Clippings from Confederate, Union, and foreign newspapers.
    Arranged, where possible, by country and by newspaper therein.
    - Southern U. S. (Box 50, Reel 27 *)
    - Northern U. S.
    - Mexico
    - France (Box 51, Reel 28 *)
    - Great Britain (Box 52, Reel 28 *)
  - James Wolcott Wadsworth Collection, 1861-1865 (Box 53-65, Reel 29-35)
    Correspondence of Department of State officials with commissioners, other officials, and agents, generally in foreign countries. This series largely duplicates material in the Diplomatic Missions and the Consular and Other Missions subseries.
    Arranged by locality and chronologically therein.
    - Correspondence with foreign agents (Box 53, Reel 29 *)
      - London, England
        - 1861-1864, James M. Mason
        - 1862-1864, Henry Hotze (Box 54, Reel 29 *)
      - Paris, France, John Slidell (Box 55A, Reel 30 *)
        - 1862-1863
        - 1863-1864 (Box 55B, Reel 30 *)
        - 1862-1864 (Box 56, Reel 31 *)
      - Belgium, 1862-1864, Dudley A. Mann (Box 57, Reel 31 *)
      - Mexico (Box 58, Reel 32 *)
        - 1861-1864, John A. Quintero
        - 1861-1865 (Box 59, Reel 32 *)
          - Avengo, Bernard
          - Fitzpatrick, Richard
          - LaSere, Emile
          - Pickett, John T.
          - Preston, William
          - Rieken, Charles
      - Miscellaneous agents, 1861-1864 (Box 60, Reel 33 *)
        - Avengo, Bernard
        - DeLeon, Edwin
        - Dowling, Robert
        - Fitzpatrick, Richard
        - Helm, Charles J.
        - Hotze, Henry
        - Lynch, P. N.
        - Mason, James M.
        - Preston, William
        - Quintero, John A.
        - Rost, Pierre A.
        - Walker, Norman J.
    - Foreign countries, 1861-1864 (Box 61, Reel 33 *)
      - Belgium
      - Cuba
      - France
      - Great Britain
      - Ireland
      - Russia
      - Spain
      - Canada (Box 62, Reel 34 *)
      - Cuba
      - Nassau
    - Extracts from letterbooks, 1861-1865 (Box 63, Reel 34 *)
      - Benjamin, Judah P.
      - Clay, Clement C.
      - Dawson, George
      - Helm, Charles J.
      - Heyliger, Lewis
      - Holcombe, James P.
      - Maury, Dabney
      - Maxwell, A. E.
      - Thompson, Jacob
    - Miscellany, 1861 (Box 64, Reel 35 *)
      - Washington commissions
      - Fort Sumter, S.C., negotiations
    - Department of the Navy, 1861-1863 (Box 65, Reel 35 *)
      - Mallory, Stephen R.
      - Semmes, Raphael
- Executive and Legislative Branches of the Confederacy, 1861-1865 (Box 66-73, Reel 35-36)
  Correspondence, messages, proclamations by Jefferson Davis, lists, memoranda, and acts and resolutions of the Confederate congress.
  - Miscellany, 1861-1865 (Box 66, Reel 35 *)
    - Annual message
    - Correspondence
    - Lists
    - Memoranda
    - Notices
    - Proclamations
    - Resolutions
    - Statutes at Large
    - Transcripts
  - Acts and Resolutions of Congress (Box 67, Reel 35 *)
    - 1861
    - 1861-1862 (Box 68, Reel 35 *)
    - 1862 (Box 69, Reel 35 *)
    - 1862 (Box 70, Reel 36 *)
    - 1863 (Box 71, Reel 36 *)
    - 1863-1864 (Box 72, Reel 36 *)
    - 1864 (Box 73, Reel 36 *)
- Confederate Constitutional Documents, 1861-1883 (Box 74-76, Reel 36-38)
  Constitutions of the Confederacy, articles of secession of the Confederate states, and related material.